[Music]
how are these orientations related to
each other if they Define the same
orientation this sign will be plus
opposite orientations this time will be
minus so we have to figure out how to
get from here to here but we
can
rearrange the
Forma into the
latter do you know this expression Forma
means what I mention before l means what
I mentioned
after L Yeah by swapping
vectors
Yeah by a sequence of transpositions
native speakers of English will call
them swaps but transpositions so I
exchange exchange exchange and if I do
an even number of
exchanges those two Define the same
orientation so the sign is plus an odd
number of exchanges it's going to be
minus it's very much similar to the
theory of determinant and this a reason
because orientation is exactly a
question whether the determinant is
positive or negative
okay and how
many
swaps how many
transpositions answer is that you
need
KL transpositions let's see an example
in
case k equals three and L is got two
yeah so I'm predicting that I need six
transpositions to go from E1 E2 E3 and
F1 let's not write those commas it's I'm
annoyed so F2 and I want to get to fub1
FS2 E1 E2 E3 I want to exchange those
sets completely so how do I do this well
first I can try to bring this over there
by exchange
those those two so the result is going
to be E1 E2 F1 E3 F2 and then I would
like to bring this over to the last
position that's another one so E1 E2
fub1 F2 E3 Ah that's good so now E3 has
come all the way out after the f1s after
the fs now I'd like to send E2 all the
way over over here so here I'm going to
do this swap the result of which is E1
fub1 E2 FS2
E3 does everyone know what we are
doing who is
lost usually I get lost when somebody
does something like this are you all
together that's amazing well okay next
I'm going to swap it over here and then
I get E1 fub1 FS2 E2 E3 that's good E2
and E3 have been sent completely to the
back so there remains for us to do this
Swap and then I'm not going to tell you
what's right out everything that happens
but at the end you get
this configuration yeah so I have
exchanged this and this to this and this
yeah and how many swaps are there
well for E3 I needed two
swaps naturally because I have to jump
over one two all the fs and then for
E2 I need no not three I just have to
jump over all the fs and I don't I don't
want to go beyond the E3 so I can just
do so 3 * 2 which is 6 which is what we
have in general the
is the same and each swap each transv
position gives a factor of minus
one so all together you get the factor
min-1 rais to^ KL and that's the end of
happy I hope
so
okay where do I go and where is the r
here
so we now know what
happens in this example instead of K
intersect L we saw we said L intersect K
we would get what kind of
result think
again no no no no no no no ah are no
please don't be confused by this okay
that's completely retive that's the case
when there's no orientability this is
all orientable please don't be confused
by such stupid things so this
is k l in this order how about l k in
this
order minus one to but what
power
no zavier what's the dimension of
K dimension of K what's the dimension of
L
no what's the dimension of L it's a
curve isn't it so what's the dimension
of
L so what factor will you
get minus one to what what what what
power K *
l 1 *
1 is it 2 no it's one so it's going to
get the factor minus one so it's going
to get be that the L inter K is going to
be minus K inter
L I told you that all of us make a
mistake thinking that this power is
minus powerus one to k + L no it's not k
+ L K * L the power that's why that was
because he was think thinking 1 + 1
that's two but it's 1 * 1 in general K *
not plus l
good
okay in this case of course that's going
to be
zero all
right okay
now the next theorem is the most
important
theorem in all of the course because
that's the foundation of the entire
theory that we'll be
using in order to topological Theory so
we should all sort of do
this it's really important theorem
have I said that it's really important
yes it is very important 3
17 and this is what it
says I'm going to discuss how the
intersection number that we have just
defined behaves when you deform
things
okay let k at L the sub manles and we
shall say oriented
closed let me underline this closed in
case you don't know what it means it
means compact without
boundary and in case you don't know what
compact without boundary means don't
worry just think boundary no
boundary
sub
yep in an Orient an oriented
manifold M okay so we are counting in
um intersection numbers by integers not
mode two just plain integers so we have
a powerful situation that's nice there
intersection
number is isotopy inv Val what does that
mean concretely it means the following
thing let's say that K is moved in space
Also that L is moved in space moved by
Isotopes okay initially before the move
K and L were intersecting a certain
pattern and you can calculate the
intersection number there in the
beginning and after the move at the end
K and L are intersecting in some other
pattern and you can count the
intersection number there after move
theorem before and after the move before
and after
intersection move isotopy the
intersection numbers are equal it does
not change that's what invariance means
so if you want to say it in sort of
formally you can say it like this if
let's say K and K1 k0 and K1 are
isotopic inside
M
and l0 and L1 are isop inside
then you can consider K k0 l0 this
intersection number so that's the
intersection number before the isotopy
also you can consider K1 and L1 the
intersection number after isotop the
claim is that they are equal I isotopy
does not change the intersection
number you you should realize that there
is an easy logical consequence of
this if you have a situation where k0
intersect some L does not equal k0 K1
intersect l or some
L then you can conclude that k0 and K K1
are not isotopic inside your
man okay because according to the
theorem if they're isotopic these two
things should be equal so this theorem
not only says that the intersection
number is isotopy invariant but also
logically trival equivalence but also
that it provide us with a tool to show
when two things are not isotopic however
hard do you
try okay
it allows us to prove impossibility
theorems okay let's draw a few examples
in order to see what it means before
proving the
result
[Music]
okay one example
I'm going to take a
Taurus and on the
Taurus something that looks a little
like the picture moment ago K going
around like this and
L going around once like
this okay and the orientation will be
the one that you na expect E1 and E2
will be like this a scene from outside
of
Taurus
okay
now I can isotope this these two curves
K and
L inside the
Taurus not outside inside the Taurus
while staying on the Taurus in the
following
manner L will still still go around
once but K instead of going just
straight across it to wiggle and then go
across and I can clearly deform K into
this position or isotope K into this
position right so that's why this
picture and this picture are isotopic to
each other if I do this what's going to
be the
intersection index like this let's put
numbers there so
k0 and L1 in the beginning and here it's
going to be K1 no not L1
l0 and here
L1 so what is k1
L1 if we go in this direction and bless
you and this
direction how many sections are there 1
2 3 before there was only one
intersection what are the signs of these
intersections k l in this dire in this
order so that's positive that's negative
that's positive so it's going to be
equal plus 1 - 1 + 1 and that's + one
whereas before this was positive so the
intersection number of k0 and l0 was
also plus one you see the intersection
number did not change when I deformed
the
picture Okay in contrast let's consider
the following
picture which in fact we met a few
examples
before although I'm going to probably do
something slightly different no it's I'm
going to do the same picture in order to
not confuse ourselves so this is let's
say
K1 but a different K1 from
above and then we are going to consider
you remember this
picture yeah and it goes around like
this round like this let's say this is
L1 so the question is can I deform this
picture to this picture in other words
in this case k seems to have stay the
same can I take this Loop and
continuously deform it isotope it with
within T2 you know make it into this
picture do you see what I'm
saying clearly if this yellow curve is
made of rubber I can deform it and
position it in this
shape can I take this pink curve and
deform it within the Taurus and put it
in this
shape the answer can be discovered by
the following argument there are one two
intersections and we have already
figured out what the signs are we saw
that this was plus one plus one right so
the here K1 intersect L1 is going to be
+ 1 + 1 = + 2 but before the
intersection number was + one after it
was
+2 that
contradicts the theorem 17 or if you
look at the parenthesis it shows that in
fact those two pictures are not isotopic
to each other therefore inside ke2 they
not
stopic okay so it's impossible however
hard you try and even if you are
geniuses to deform this picture to this
this picture it's an impossibility so
let me write this k0 and K L1 isal plus
okay that's how you use this theorem I
hope the um example is
clear
okay yes
in high
dimension asks whether this deformation
is possible in higher dimensional space
let me it's an excellent question let me
modify the question slightly but it's
the same question suppose that you see
here I'm always writing carefully
writing inside T2 inside
T2 yeah suppose that I can go outside
T2 well then effectively think of this
as a rub band hooked on a Taurus and
then I can stretch the rub band and I
can maybe imagine a station like this
the ruband goes you know now
outside T2 you see it's no longer
touching T2 it's no longer on T2 and
then I might want to rearrange this but
you see even so I cannot rearrange in a
configuration like
this it's I think very difficult however
suppose that you have not only R3 you
see here I have come out from T2 to the
ambient R3 suppose that I have I am
inside
r
five then I can take
this rubber band and take it off the
Taurus without intersecting the Taurus
why because this curve has M what's the
dimension of this
curve what's the dimension of this
Surface Two 1 + 2
that's three so if I have a
four-dimensional space they Sorry
threedimensional space they should
intersect generically but if I have a
four dimensional space they don't
intersect but if I have a five
dimensional space I can move one away
from without interseting this is what we
proved yesterday so if you have a high
dimensional space the Overflow becomes
minus one or less in fact minus two and
or less so I can move it so in five
diamension five I think you can move it
away okay if I move this one dimensional
thing it's going to sweep out the
surface which has Dimension
two one dimensional thing moving the
screen that the sheet that you sweep out
is dimension
two this surface Taurus has Dimension
two and I want to avoid having the
Taurus and this sheet intersecting two
and two don't intersect in five
dimensions and
above are you okay in dimension four two
and two intersecting points in Zero
Dimensional
things but in five dimensional above two
and two don't intersect so I can move
this without intersecting taus and then
I can put it I can deform it in any
shape and then put it back so that's
possible so if I'm not on the Taurus but
if I'm moving if I'm move inside a
higher dimensional space I can do this
so you see it's important to specify in
which ambient space you are doing all
these
operations whether the operation is
possible or not depends on how much room
how much Freedom you you have around you
is that clear
okay
good in order to understand better the
this kind of dimension count you should
do the project that I gave yesterday you
remember so this
is a two Twisted movie
strip and I asked you in what are n RM
these two can become
isotopic that's a very interesting
problem and by studying it you'll
understand quite a lot of these
things okay
one more
to results to consolidate our
picture
okay we have
to first
remark that in the theorem I underlined
this word
closed K and L are supposed to be
closed that word is very important in
order to guarantee that the result isop
invariance
holds the closed
this by the way when I say closed I keep
saying but I don't mean closed in the
sense of General topology Point set
topology I don't mean the complement of
an open set I mean compact without
boundary in case this kind of language
makes sense if it doesn't then just
relax okay Clos this
hypothesis in theorum
17 is essential you
cannot State a theorem without that
word indeed
for some manifolds without W boundary
excuse
me the intersection
number may not be isop invariant
okay when I write something like this
that for nonclosed sub manif fors the
isop uh the intersection number may not
be I to be invariant what is your first
request your first request if you're a
good scientist
and not just students sitting in class
listening to a
teacher if you're a good scientist pleas
show us an
example where it's not nice to be
invariant because the manifolds are not
closed that should be your first
instinct and often textbook writers
monograph writers paper writers and
lecturers and so on do not show you an
example after they make a claim what do
you do in that case you either raise
your hand and say please show us an
example
or you try to construct an example
yourself okay under no circumstance
should you just read this and say okay
and go
on examples examples examples good
examples intelligent examples
informative examples that's what
learning science in general and in
particular mathematics is all about
memorizing a 100
abstract theorems will not get you
anywhere as creative scientists one
example is worth a thousand
theorems good example so let's see an
example let's take two sub manifolds one
of them is closed this
is K it's just a cirle you can imagine
these things to live inside R3 okay but
the other
some manifold is a sheet of
paper okay and which I called that
L this is closed but this sheet of paper
is not closed because it has a boundary
this is the boundary the edge of the
paper okay and this K intersects the
paper K intersects l in one po it goes
around and and then goes around okay
that's the picture
so this has
boundary in other words it's not closed
enough terminology whereas this K has no
boundary so it's um it's fine so let's
move this K grab this and then just move
it
sideways that's an isotopy of course
initially the intersection number
between K and L is going to be well I
didn't specify the orientation but it's
going to be plus or minus one because
there's only one point and if I move it
eventually what's going to
happen is
that come we come a point where K gets
disconnected from from L going
yeah and at that
moment K intersect L will be
zero although this was a perfectly good
isotopy I just moved K while fixing
l so you see before
and after the isotopy the intersection
number
changed intersection number was not
isotopy invariant what happened well
what happened is that L had a boundary
and you see this intersection Point came
closer and closer near and nearer the
boundary boundary and eventually reached
the boundary and poof fell off the
boundary it disappeared because it cross
the
boundary okay so the
intersection should I say fell off
the
boundary okay that's what can happen so
we must make sure that in applying this
theorem the boundaries are absent so
that you cannot fall off
the you notice that we are still
discussing examples and we have not yet
proved this most important theorem
theorem 17 we are still trying to
understand all the circumstances in
which the theorem work works and those
circumstances in which the theorem can
fail we shall come to the proof of that
theorem in a very short while
and
okay right I keep saying okay
today yet one more statement before we
come to the proof of
17 the cor of this if you believe that
this theorem is true yeah is
that in the non- transversal station you
remember there was a problem about the
non- transversal station you had
to deform the non transversal station
into transversality and count
intersection
number and there a question as to
whether the intersection number that you
get depended or not on the way you
deform I claimed earlier that you should
see cor 20 to check that it's
independent and now is the time to say
that it is independent in the non
transversal
stations of definition 12 I think so
that's when K and L were not
intersecting transversally
as
n Now
read still K intersect L is well
defined
independently of
how we
deform into transvers
and what's your comment about this
sentence it's misspelled independent
three thank you very much I hope that
now all of us French speakers know about
this
okay okay so that's clear because you
see when you deform in fact you are
performing an isotopy so suppose that
you can deform a non transversal station
into to one transversal station and to
another transversal station and I like
show that the intersection number in
this case and in this section number in
this case are the same intersection
number independent of how we deed but
that's easy because I can reverse the
isotopy from this station to this
station and then connect it to this
station and in the course of this
isotopy the intersection number is
invariant so that means that this number
equals this number okay so that's a
trival consequence
good we shall
then um finish with the proof
of the theorem 17 for
today so we have understood all of these
hopefully so now proof of theorem 17
which as we mentioned is the most
important theorem in all of this course
it's actually not difficult to
understand and why it's true and that's
how we shall prove it if you start doing
all the details set theoretic details if
you want to express everything in terms
of SE Theory and so on it becomes
complicated but the intuition is clear
enough first it's enough to prove
[Applause]
this when we
isotope just okay
so what I mean is instead of moving both
K and L let's just move um K because
then you know k0 intersect L will be the
same as K1 intersect L and then we can
now move L and then it would still be
the same by the same so I'm going to
assume that L does not move but K is
being moved okay
now that two phases in this Motion in
this
isotopy while the K and L intersect
transversally the intersection number a
intersection number does not
change that's clear for example let's
see that this is l
and this
is
K okay so it's intersecting there and
then let's say the K moves from this
position to this position and then
intersection moves from here to here but
it's clear if this intersection was
positive by moving it continuously it's
still positive yeah there's no problem
about just slightly part in the um the
picture so the intersection number does
not change
while they transverse to each other but
an interesting problem occurs when you
lose transversity and after all
sometimes you have to go through non
transversal
situations so what happens when you come
across a crisis when you become non-
transversal but when at the
moment we pass
through a
moment of non
transversality what happens here is a
typical picture of what happens let's
say that this is
L and K looks like this and there's a
point here Point here and let's say that
this intersection is um plus and this
intersection is minus let's see okay and
then I start moving K
gradually and then I keep moving
K like
this very similar what we did over there
I just move it and this is
transversal that's transversal that the
middle picture is not transversal right
so you
go out
boom that's how it works now this is not
transversal because it's there's a
tangency
there but see what happens here the
there was
transversality non transversality and
transversal okay but what happened is
that here you had the
plus and minus which is equal to zero
and those plus and minus as you pull up
come closer and closer
together and finally
meet Co Le in the non- transversal
moment and then poof they disappear in a
puff of
smoke so as to become zero similarly if
you reverse the
movie imagine taking K and lowering it
to L then it's 0 0 0 there's no
intersection there's no intersection and
at some point there's a
tangency something happens and a pair of
plus and minus appear out of
zero this is what happens always in fact
in such
situations and I'm going to continue the
uh
proof down here so that
it turns out that when you pass through
moments of non
transversality there was I there's
always either a
pairwise anation or pairwise
creation we
either so please um understand that this
goes to this Blackboard that's the
statement of the theorem and this is a
proof of the theorem okay so we
either
create
or who knows this word anate annihilate
which means destroy okay but that's the
traditional scientific term for the
opposite of create create or
annihilate a
pair of um intersection points
of opposite
sides
okay and the picture that you should
have in mind is the physics
one have you heard about particles and
anti
particles so electron and poon for
example or proton and the antiproton and
things like this so if you
have a particle and it's anti
particle encounter each other what
happens they disappear in a PA of smoke
leaving on the
energy conversely there are mechanisms
in high energy physics where you can
shake the vacuum and if you have enough
energy a pair of particle and anti
particle appear That's why in science
fiction it's often said that if Tadashi
goes to some somewh very very far away
and meet a copy of Tadashi but made of
anti particles antiprotons anti neutrons
and so on it's very dangerous to try to
shake hands because then you poof so
these two things can go between so
Vacuum Plus Pure
Energy anyway so from nothing you can
have a pair of something and from
something you can get nothing but you
have to be careful that from nothing you
cannot get just a particle you always
have to have plus and minus so that the
total sum is conserved yeah you cannot
get one out of zero but you can get plus
one and minus one two of them out of
zero and that's what happens effectively
so the sign of all the signs
of KT and L remains unchanged and that's
the um end of the proof Remains the
Same okay we have now proved that the
intersection number is isotopy invariant
for closed
submanifolds and this is the central
theorem the theorical tool which we
shall use time and again to deduce an
enormous and very interesting variety of
applications of topology to mathematics
and Natural Sciences in general